A Guide to the Papers of John Paul Carter, 1965-1997
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Papers of John Paul Carter 1965-1997
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 63
This collection consists of 1 Hollinger Document Case. .38 Linear Feet.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open to researchers without restrictions. Questions about literary property rights should be directed to the Special Collections Coordinator.
Biographical/Historical Information
John Paul Carter was born May 14, 1923 in Clarksburg, West Virginia. He was the oldest child of the Rev. Josiah Tidbal Carter and Virginia Rutherford Nolting. He had two younger brothers, James and Josiah, and two sisters, Virginia and Louise. John was always known as "Jack", probably because his grandfather and uncle shared his name. Carter married in 1947. He and his wife, Joan, had six children together.
In his youth, Jack attended public schools in Clarksburg. He decided long before college that he wanted to be part of the ministry. He was accepted to both Harvard and William and Mary. Because of the financial assistance it offered, he chose to attend William and Mary. In college, Carter was involved many extracurricular activities. He was President of the class of 1945, member and officer of the biology club, and choir member in the Bruton Parish Church. He was active in the Canterbury Club. He also started a football team. Carter graduated in June 2, 1944. After graduation, he went to the Virginia Theological Seminary.
In 1947, Carter was ordained in his father's church in Durham, North Carolina. He went on to become deacon-in-charge of St. James Kannapolis, St. Paul's, and St. Peter's Salisbury. Five years later, Carter accepted a job as the Episcopal Chaplain to the University of Texas. There he put his energy into church reform.
In 1964, Carter accepted a job with the Airlie Foundation in Warrenton, Virginia. The Airlie Foundation was a "think tank" organization. Airlie served as an innkeeper for a number of National and Washington organizations, and they generated meetings between people with similar liberal/populist ideas. There Carter met Henry Berne and Max Tuffs. They were all very active in opposition to Massive Resistance and in Community Action. Among other things, they "preached" and spoke politically at Black churches, wrote position papers, and campaigned for Henry Howell and for George Rowling. After a year, Carter left Airlee. He went back to working for the Episcopal Church. There he served as Secretary/Treasurer of the National Association of Episcopal Schools.
In 1979, Carter received his Ph.D. After graduation, he became assistant to the President of Mary Baldwin College. He resigned this position after six weeks. Carter then moved to Maryland, and served at St. John's in Ellicoll City. Eventually, he became a rector there.
Retiring in 1987, Carter moved to Sewanee, Tennessee. In 1997, Carter died of pulmonary fibrosis.
Scope and Content Information
The Carter papers date from 1965 to 1997, although the main focus is on the late 1960's and early 1970's. These papers deal mainly with the Airlie Group, Democratic politics, and Henry Howell's gubernatorial campaigns.
Organization
These papers are divided into five series: I. Correspondence; II. Airlie Group; III. Henry Howell; IV. Politics; and V. News Clippings.
Series I: Correspondence
Correspondence dates from 1965-1996. Material from the late 1960's and early 1970's pertains to: Airlie Foundation business, meetings, and conferences; Liberal Democratic political strategy; redistricting; the poll tax; populism; the Byrd Organization in Virginia; allocation of State surplus funds in 1965; revision of the Virginia election laws; and the political campaigns of Henry Howell and George Rawlings. Later material from the mid-1970's through the mid-1990's is largely personal correspondence with some references to politics.
Series II: Airlie Group
This series includes agendas, minutes, conference/meeting registration forms, notes, and an essay on Virginia. Topics include: Virginia politics, integration, candidates for office, and other Airlie business. Material dates from 1965-66.
Series III: Henry Howell
This series pertains specifically to Henry Howell. Information includes: a 1967 appeal brief by Henry Howell to the Supreme Court of Appeals in Virginia regarding Virginia automobile insurance rate increases; campaign photographs; Henry Howell's Action Program for Virginia in 1969; Howell's campaign newsletter from 1973; the program for Henry Howell's inauguration as Lieutenant Governor of Virginia in 1971; and his campaign speeches. Material dates from 1965-73.
Series IV: Politics
This series contains: an undated list of Clarke County Democratic members; Virginia Democratic Party Organization Plan (as adopted June 9, 1932); 1966 election results from the 8th District Democratic Primary; "Rawlings for Senate" campaign material from 1966 and 1970; a press release and campaign flyer for "Bingo" Stant for Congress; a Democratic precinct worker's handbook from 1965; material on redistricting Virginia in 1966 and 1971; an outline on a seminar on Virginia State government in 1965; and Virginia Independent newsletters from 1991. This series also includes news clippings and notes. Material dates from 1965-71. One folder has material from 1991.
Series V: News Clippings
This series contains: news clippings on the 1966 Democratic Primary and General Assembly Session; Henry Howell's election as Lt. Governor in 1971; various other clippings on Mr. Howell in the 1970's; and Henry Howell's obituary from 1997. Material dates sporadically from 1966 to 1997.
Container List
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence, June-Sept. 1965 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Correspondence, Oct. 1965 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Correspondence-between George Rawlings and Governor Harrison, July-August 1965, re. Allocation of state surplus (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Correspondence, Nov.-Dec. 1965 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-May 1966 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Correspondence, June-July 1966 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Correspondence, Aug.-Dec. 1966 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Correspondence, [Jan.-Feb.], Aug. 1967 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Correspondence, Feb.-Mar. 1969 re. Howell's 1969 Gubernatorial campaign (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Correspondence, Dec. 1971-May 1973 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1996 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Correspondence, Henry Howell to Reverend John Paul Carter, 28 December 1983 with accompanying newsclippings and articles (Box-folder 1:12)
- Airlie Group
  - Agenda-Airlie Group Meeting-Richmond, Jan. 1966 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Minutes-Airlie Group Meeting, Oct. 1965, re. actions of liberal Democrats in 1966 Democratic primary (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Minutes-Airlie Group Meeting-Charlottesville, July 1966, re. results of 1966 Democratic primary (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Notes on Telephone Conversations, Nov. 1965-Jan. 1966, re. the running of liberal Democratic candidates in 1966 Democratic primary (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Registration-Airlie Group Meeting, Oct. 1965 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Registration-Airlie Group Meeting, Jan. 1966 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Registration-Airlie Group Meeting, July 1966 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - "Virginia At Mid-Century Plus 15 "-Airlie Foundation, 27 March 1965 (Box-folder 1:20)
- Henry Howell
  - Appeal Brief-Henry Howell, et. al. v. State Corporation Commission, 1967 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Henry Howell-Campaign Photographs, n.d. (Box-folder 1:22)
  - The Finest of Tomorrow-Henry Howell's Action Program for Virginia, 1969 (Box-folder 1:23)
  - The Howell Campaigner, 1973 (Box-folder 1:24)
  - Henry Howell-Inauguration as Lt. Governor, 1971 (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Speeches-Henry Howell, Oct.-Dec. 1965 (Box-folder 1:26)
  - Speeches-Henry Howell, May 1969 (Box-folder 1:27)
- Politics
  - Clarke County Democratic Committee, List of Members, n.d. (Box-folder 1:28)
  - "Democratic Party Plans: Plan of Organization and Primary Plan of the Democratic Party of Virginia" (Box-folder 1:29)
  - Election Results, 1966 8th District Democratic primary (Box-folder 1:30)
  - George Rawlings-Campaign Material, 1966 and 1970 (Box-folder 1:31)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 1:32)
  - Precinct Worker's Handbook, Sept. 1965 (Box-folder 1:33)
  - Press Release-June 1968 re. "Bingo" Stant (Box-folder 1:34)
  - Redistricting in Virginia, 1966 (I) (Box-folder 1:35)
  - Redistricting in Virginia, 1966 (II) (Box-folder 1:36)
  - Redistricting in Virginia, 1971 (Box-folder 1:37)
  - "Seminar on State Government" by Prof. E.A. Means, 12 June 1965 (Box-folder 1:38)
  - "Virginia Independent, Apr., Oct. 1991 (Box-folder 1:39)
- News Clippings
  - 1966 General Assembly session (Box-folder 1:40)
  - 1966 Democratic primary (Box-folder 1:41)
  - Howell's Election as Lt. Governor, 1971 (Box-folder 1:42)
  - Henry Howell 1973, 1977, 1978 (Box-folder 1:43)
  - Henry Howell obituaries, 1997 (Box-folder 1:44)